Wayne C. Taylor Papers
Wayne C. Taylor Papers
1927-1960
1940-1955
Taylor, Wayne Chatfield, 1893-1967.
8.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American economist, banker; advisor on trade issues to Franklin D. Roosevelt. Correspondence, memoranda, speeches, and government publications relating to Taylor's work as an investment banker and economic advisor. Includes material relating to commerce, foreign investment, and the National Planning Association.
148699
Biographical History
Wayne Chatfield Taylor (1893-1967) was an American economic advisor and banker. He was born in Chicago, Illinois on December 19, 1893. He received a B.A. degree from Yale University in 1916. He began his banking career with the Central Trust Company of Illinois. In 1923 he became vice-president of Marshall Field, Glore, Ward and Company, investment bankers. From 1935 to 1936 he was the vice-president and trustee of the Export-Import Bank of Washington, DC, and he became president in 1945. He was also a member of the Board of Directors of Encyclopaedia Britannica Films and a delegate for the American Red Cross.
Taylor held many advisory and administrative positions in the presidential administrations of both Franklin D. Roosevelt and Harry S. Truman. In 1933 he began as an assistant to the administrator of the Agricultural Adjustment Administration. From 1936 to 1939 he was the assistant Secretary of the Treasury. From 1940 to 1945 he was Under Secretary of Commerce. From 1948-1950 he was an assistant to Paul G. Hoffman, the European Cooperation Administrator. He was also a trustee on the Committee for Economic Development, the chairman of the executive committee of the National Planning Association, and a consultant to the War Assets Administration. He represented the United States at many international trade conferences and acted as an economic adviser to the European Recovery Program after World War II.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Wayne C Taylor Papers contains materials relating to Taylor's work as an investment banker and economic advisor. Items in the Correspondence and subject files include correspondence, manuscripts, speeches, memoranda, booklets, reports, and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Items are arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent, organization, or subject. Speeches are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization or conference at which they were given.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Business and Industry; Taylor, Wayne Chatfield, 1893-1967.; National Planning Association.; Montgomery Ward.; American Red Cross.; Benton, William, 1900-1973.; Messersmith, George S. (George Strausser), 1883-1960.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; United States -- Commerce.; United States -- Economic policy -- 1933-1945.; United States -- Economic policy -- 1945-1960.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1953.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; Bankers -- United States.; Economists -- United States.; Investments, American.; Marshall Plan.; Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Speeches (documents); Bankers.; Economists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence and subject files
  - A - general, 1947-1953 (Box 1)
  - A - miscellaneous, 1940-1953 (Box 1)
  - ATA final, 1942 (Box 1)
  - American Consulate General (Latin America), 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - American overseas aid, 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Red Cross
    - 1948-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Business, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Files, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - General, 1941-1945 (Box 1)
    - Mission, 1940 (Box 1)
  - B - general, 1951-1953 (Box 2)
  - B - miscellaneous, 1940-1955 (Box 2)
  - Barber, Maurice, 1943-1949 (Box 2)
  - Barrett, Wendell, 1940-1945 (Box 2)
  - Benton, William
    - 1944-1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Commission on Government, 1944 (Box 2)
    - Confidential, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - Bretton Woods statements, 1945; See also United Nations: Monetary Conference - Bretton Woods, N.H. (Box 2)
  - British - correspondence, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Burgess, E. W., 1947-1952 (Box 2)
  - Business notes, undated (Box 2)
  - C - general, 1950-1955 (Box 2)
  - C - miscellaneous, 1943-1948 (Box 2)
  - Carbons, Daily, 1933-1934 (Box 2)
  - Charlottesville, Va., 1949 (Box 3)
  - Chicago investors, 1929-1932 (Box 3)
  - Chicago - letters received from, 1927-1929 (Box 3)
  - Conference of American Republics - foreign ministers, Mexico City, February 21, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Congressional Record Digest, 1944 (Box 3)
  - D - miscellaneous, 1944-1955 (Box 3)
  - de Basily, Nicholas, 1942-1948; See also Taylor, Wayne C.: de Basily, correspondence with (Box 3)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1942-1954 (Box 3)
  - E - miscellaneous, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - E-I and SAFT official correspondence A-Z, 1934-1935 (Box 3)
  - Emory University, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Encyclopedia Britannica Films, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - European Recovery Program, 1948; See also Marshall Plan (Box 3)
  - F - general, 1952-1954 (Box 3)
  - F - miscellaneous, 1943-1954 (Box 3)
  - Fairs, trade (Hartigan, etc.), 1935-1951 (Box 3)
  - Federal City Council, 1952-1959 (Box 4)
  - Last years in FOA (Foreign Operations Administration), 1950-1954 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Service Educational Foundation, 1943-1947 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Trade Administration proposed by George Peek, 1953 (Box 4)
  - French matters, 1941-1945 (Box 4)
  - G - general, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - Gassette, Grace, 1941-1947 (Box 4)
  - Germany - cotton, 1935-1936 (Box 4)
  - H - miscellaneous, 1941-1953 (Box 4)
  - Hartigan, John D., 1951-1955; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Hellier, Walter, 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Hewes, Thomas, 1942-1954 (Box 4)
  - I-J - general, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - I-J - miscellaneous, 1940-1946 (Box 5)
  - Inter-American Conference, 1945 (Box 5)
  - International Hudson Corporation, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - International Trade Comm. of Advertising Club, NYC, 1949 (Box 5)
  - Italian financial matters, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
  - Jewelers Acceptance Corporation, 1956-1958 (Box 5)
  - K - miscellaneous, 1941-1953 (Box 5)
  - Kenney - memorandums for, 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Knowles, Mr. and Mrs. Carroll W., 1943-1949 (Box 5)
  - L - miscellaneous, 1945-1955 (Box 5)
  - LaVarre, William - miscellaneous letters, 1944 (Box 5)
  - M - miscellaneous, 1940-1955 (Box 5)
  - Mc and Mac - miscellaneous, 1940-1948 (Box 5)
  - Marshall Plan, See also European Recovery Program
    - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
    - CED (Committee on European Development), 1947 (Box 6)
    - NPA (National Planning Association), 1947; See also NPA (National Planning Association) (Box 6)
    - Pre 1947-1948 (Box 6)
  - Meeker, Lawrence A., 1943 (Box 6)
  - Messersmith, George S., 1941-1948 (Box 6)
  - Mexican-American Commission for Economic Cooperation report, 1943 (Box 6)
  - Mexican matters, 1943-1945 (Box 7)
  - Mexico Light, 1956-1959 (Box 7)
  - Minott, James, 1951-1953 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - 1931-1936 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1953 (Box 7)
    - Items, 1939-1950 (Box 7)
    - Letters, 1932 (Box 7)
    - Letters - ECA (European Corporation Administration), 1945-1948 (Box 7)
    - Letters, 1939 (Box 7)
    - Manuscripts in package, undated (Box 7)
    - Organizations, 1956-1958 (Box 7)
    - Papers, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
    - Reports, pamphlets, etc., 1936-1939 (Box 8)
  - Montgomery Ward & Company
    - Anonymous letters, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Chicago, Illinois, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Court matters, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Fan mail, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Management, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Official, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Newspaper and clippings, 1944 (Box 8)
    - Signed letters from public, 1944 (Box 8)
  - N - miscellaneous, 1941-1951 (Box 9)
  - NPA (National Planning Association), See also Marshall Plan: NPA (National Planning Organization)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 9)
    - Brazil, 1957 (Box 9)
    - Case studies, 1957-1959 (Box 9)
    - Liberia, 1956-1957 (Box 9)
    - Charles Symington project, 1951-1953 (Box 9)
  - 0 - miscellaneous, 1941-1955 (Box 9)
  - OEEC meetings and conference in London, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - P & Q - miscellaneous, 1940-1955 (Box 9)
  - Mr. Peek memoranda, 1934-1936 (Box 9)
  - Peoples Trust & Savings Bank, 1932 (Box 9)
  - Personnel Reserve Corps, 1951 (Box 9)
  - Pierson, John, 1953-1955 (Box 9)
  - "The Position of British Overseas Investments, 1919-1943" by Donald F. Heatherington-BFDC (Box 9)
  - R - general, 1952-1955 (Box 9)
  - R - miscellaneous, 1940-1953 (Box 9)
  - Releases, departmental - Committee for Economic Development, 1943 (Box 9)
  - RIO Conference, 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D. Foundation, 1948-1953 (Box 10)
  - Roosevelt for President Campaign, 1932-1933 (Box 10)
  - Roper, Elmo, 1953 (Box 10)
  - S - general, 1951-1953 (Box 10)
  - S - miscellaneous, 1943-1951 (Box 10)
  - Service Bureau for Women's Organizations, 1951-1952 (Box 10)
  - Small business, 1944 (Box 10)
  - L. Smit correspondence, 1950-1953 (Box 10)
  - Society of the Cincinnati, 1941-1949 (Box 10)
  - South American problems correspondence, 1940 (Box 10)
  - Speeches
    - American Association of Collegiate Schools of Business, Lexington, Va., address, April 24, 1942 (Box 10)
    - American Business Congress, New York City, address, November 19, 1942 (Box 10)
    - American Congress, New York City, remarks, March 17, 1944 (Box 10)
    - American Forum of the Air, Washington, D.C., May 10, 1942 (Box 10)
    - American Forum of the Air, March 28, 1943 (Box 10)
    - American Institute of Banking, New York City, February 2, 1946 (Box 10)
    - American Lesion Post, address, November 7, 1941 (Box 10)
    - American 'Marine Conference, New York City, address, October 20, 1944 (Box 10)
    - D.C. Bankers Association, speech, January 21, 1946 (Box 10)
    - 14th Annual Boston Conference on Distribution Boston, Mass., address, October 5, 1942 (Box 10)
    - Breakfast Club of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, Calif., radio address, April 15, 1942 (Box 10)
    - Building & Loan League speech material, Miami, Florida, cancelled, December 5, 1941 (Box 10)
    - Business Forum Broadcast, Radio Station WMCA, New York City, on small business, October 25, 1944 (Box 10)
    - Business Forum Broadcast, New York City, November 13, 1945 (Box 10)
    - Canadian Chamber of Commerce, Ottawa, Can., address, September 17, 1941 (Box 10)
    - Chemical Association Panel, New York City, November 24, 1953 (Box 10)
    - Chicago Association of Commerce, Chicago, Ill., address, February 6, 1941 (Box 10)
    - Chicago World Trade Conference, Chicago, Ill., address, February 14, 1944 (Box 10)
    - Christ Church Forum, New York City, address, September 15, 1943 (Box 10)
    - Conference of Retail Merchants for the Northwest, Minneapolis, Minn., address, August 26, 1942 (Box 10)
    - Cotton Textile Institute, New York City, remarks, October 20, 1943 (Box 10)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, New York City, speech, January 22, 1946 (Box 10)
    - Credit Men's Association of Eastern Pa., speech, November 1, 1945 (Box 10)
    - Demobilization of Wartime Economic Controls (Box 11)
    - First National Negro Business Conference, speech, April 18, 1941 (Box 11)
    - Merrill Foundation, private investment (Box 11)
    - Mexico Pilgrims, New York City, address, September 16, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Mississippi Valley Association, St. Louis, Missouri, address, October 18, 1943 (Box 11)
    - National Council of American Importers, New York City, speech, April 24, 1941 (Box 11)
    - National Foreign Trade Convention, Boston, Mass., address, October 7, 1942 (Box 11)
    - National Foreign Trade Convention, New York City, speech, November 13, 1945 (Box 11)
    - National Foreign Trade Council, New York City, address, October 8, 1941 (Box 11)
    - National Industrial Advertisers Assn., Chicago, Ill., address, March 13, 1942 (Box 11)
    - New Orleans Association of Commerce luncheon meeting, New Orleans, La., address, November 30, 1944 (Box 11)
    - New York Board of Trade, New York City, address, October 21, 1942 (Box 11)
    - New York State Maritime Academy, Fort Schuyler, N. Y., address, April 26, 1944 (Box 11)
    - Norfolk Association of Commerce, Norfolk, Va., address, December 8, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Pan American Day, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, Calif., April 14, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Philadelphia Plan for Wartime Business Clinics, Philadelphia, Pa., address, September 15, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Society for Advancement of Management, Washington, D.C., forum meeting, November 15, 1944 (Box 11)
    - Society for Advancement of Management, New York City, address, November 18, 1944 (Box 11)
    - Society for Advancement of Management Conference, Washington, D.C., remarks, May 26, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Southern Political Science Association, Lexington, Va., speech, October 21, 1948 (Box 11)
    - Speeches - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Tampa Chamber of Commerce, Tampa, Florida, address, March 31, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Town Hall Foreign Trade Week Observance, Los Angeles, Calif., address, May 17, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Town Hall, Inc., discussion program New York City, address, November 23, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Trade Association speech, Washington, D.C., April 28, 1941 (Box 11)
    - U.S. Junior Chamber of Commerce, Dallas, Texas, address, June 18, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Virginia Manufacturers Association, Roanoke, Va., address, October 17-18, 1941 (Box 11)
    - Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, Richmond, Va., address (Box 11)
    - War Restrictions in Commerce, Federal-State Conference on, Washington, D.C., address, May 7, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Washington Board of Trade Meeting, Washington, D.C., remarks, January 16, 1945 (Box 11)
    - Washington, D.C., radio broadcast, (Jobs after the War) (Box 11)
    - Women's National Democratic Club, talk, December 9, 1940 (Box 11)
    - World Trade Luncheon of National Foreign Trade Week, New York City, address, May 16, 1942 (Box 11)
    - Station WOR, radio speech, October 26, 1940 (Box 11)
    - Station WOR, radio speech, October 30, 1940 (Box 11)
    - World Statesmen: "Post-War Planning on the Home Front," Radio Station WWDC program, Washington, D.C., September 28, 1943 (Box 11)
    - Weather Bureau, Washington, D.C. (Box 11)
  - State Department (Dumbarton Oaks Conference), 1944-1945 (Box 11)
  - Storms, Alice, 1941-1945 (Box 11)
  - T - miscellaneous, 1941-1952 (Box 11)
  - Taylor, Wayne C.
    - Charity contributions, 1936-1938 (Box 11)
    - Congratulations - acknowledgments, 1940 (Box 12)
    - Congratulatory correspondence, 1945 (Box 12)
    - Congratulations - nomination, 1940 (Box 12)
    - de Basily, correspondence with, 1927-1928; See also de Basily, Nicholas (Box 12)
    - Letters, business, 1927-1929 (Box 12)
    - Letters from friends and acquaintances, 1944 (Box 12)
    - Marshall Field
      - Chicago, letters to, 1927-1929 (Box 12)
      - New York, letters to, 1927-1929 (Box 12)
    - Memorandums - Taylor's, 1933 (Box 12)
    - Notebook of W. Taylor, 1932 (Box 12)
    - Notes on miscellaneous items, 1934 (Box 13)
    - Personal
      - Mr. Taylor, 1927-1929; 1934-1937; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Data, 1933-1935 (Box 13)
      - File, 1929 (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous, 1933-1959; 2 folders (Box 13)
      - "Thank you", 1946 (Box 13)
    - Random notes, 1931-1933 (Box 13)
    - Report - Taylor's to Mr. Hoffman, August 1949 (Box 14)
    - Resignation from Treasury - Mr. Taylor's, 1939 (Box 14)
    - Semi-personal - Wayne C. Taylor, 1948-1951 (Box 14)
    - State Dept. Press Release, 1942 (Box 14)
  - "Taylor" - miscellaneous, 1941 (Box 14)
  - Taylor, Wayne Chatfield, 1949-1952 (Box 14)
  - Treasury - proposed bank for reconstruction development, 1944 (Box 14)
  - Trips taken - Wayne C. Taylor, 1929 (Box 14)
  - U-V - miscellaneous, 1940-1948 (Box 14)
  - Under Secretary of Commerce, 1941-1945 (Box 15)
  - United Nations
    - 1952-1945 (Box 15)
    - Monetary Conference - Bretton Woods, N.H., July 1, 1944; 1943-1945; See also Bretton Woods statements (Box 15)
    - Stabilization - preliminary draft, 1942 (Box 15)
  - W - miscellaneous, 1940-1954 (Box 15)
  - W - Y miscellaneous, 1933-1938 (Box 15)
  - Waddington, John, 1942-1953 (Box 15)
  - War Assets Administration, 1946-1947 (Box 15)
  - The White House, 1941-1945 (Box 15)
  - Wiley, ambassador, 1945-1953 (Box 15)
  - Wilson, Carroll S., 1953-1954 (Box 16)
  - Winston, Farwell, 1941-1952 (Box 16)
  - World Trade Center, San Francisco, 1952-1953 (Box 16)
  - Wright, William V. D. (National City Bank, N. Y.), 1940-1942 (Box 16)
  - Yale institute of International Studies, 1939 (Box 16)
  - Yale University - miscellaneous, 1941-1953 (Box 16)